hello and welcome to the lecture where we explore microprocessors by learning machine language and
assembly language and reimplementing software in the lowest possible language so we're going to start
with our two instruction CPU from the previous section and look kind of what it did and what it
didn't do because our next CPU is going to have more data we're going to have to learn hexadecimal
notation instead of base two and then we're going to take a look at the foundations of programming
from python for everybody sequential conditional and iteration based programming and then we're
going to reimplement all those things in machine language and assembly language we'll take a look
at real CPUs that are in the market now like Intel x86 and ARM and then a historical CPU the 6502
the CPU that we're going to simulate and build is called the cd i called it the cdc 6504 it really
is mostly a 6502 with some homage to the first machine language that i ever knew which was the
cdc 6500 so we're going to learn about the architecture registers those kinds of things
and then machine language the actual zeros and ones that the the 6502 executes and then
assembly language it's a very low level language which has a one-to-one correspondence with machine
language and after we've played with an emulator long enough we'll realize that you know emulators
can be a pretty cool thing and they're actually not that hard to not that hard to write and we'll
look at some of the emulators like WASM emulators and JavaScript we'll take a look at how
internet archive keeps old games alive using a series of emulators that run all inside your browser
and then we're going to finish up talking about CPU evolution over the decades so if we take a
look at the end of the lecture in the previous section we had built a CPU that had in effect
one four bit register one four bit adder a clock and then one instruction that chose between whether
or not we reset the register the latch or we incremented the latch and interestingly that's
where we're going to start but like what is missing and and the answer is if we go all the
way back to chapter 1 slide 19 python for everybody a class that i started teaching in the mid 2000s
basically what we're missing is instructions that are coming from the main memory to program the
central processing unit and those instructions guide the central processing unit as to how to
use the hardware inside that central processing unit and those instructions are zeros and ones
that are represented by electrical impulses that are coming into the central processor
if we look at a little more detail in the central processor there's a number of different
resources in the central processor there is the alu the arithmetic and logic unit which has adders
comparison multipliers sometimes and then there is a place we stored super fast data to feed to and
from alu the registers so usually the alu doesn't operate on things that are in the memory we load
data into the registers and then we do computations with the alu the pc our program counter is the
most important register of all because it tells the cpu where in the memory to retrieve the next
instruction so based on where the pc is pointing the cpu retrieves an instruction from the memory
and they register the cir current instruction register which is not shown on a lot of architecture
diagrams but in a sense the the machine code the 816 or more bits is loaded into the cpu in a
register and then it does what's called decoding and that is it looks at the bits says is this an
add is this a subtract is this an increment is this a clear what is the instruction and then what
the decoder does is it in effect sends signals to the rest of the parts of the central processing unit
to say oh okay we're going to add so take this register feed it to the alu add this other register
and then take the result from that addition and put it into a different register and of course
there's a clock and the clock causes the logic to happen our emulator is going to run on a one
hertz clock which is one one instruction per second and the real 6502 is one megahertz which
is a million instructions per second which of course compared to modern processors is not very
many so the machine language instructions that we're going to do are going to be eight bits
and there is an assembly language which is a symbolic representation like if we want to clear
the x register set it to zero then we have an opcode of one one one zero zero zero one zero
and so you can just see these opcodes for various things there's a clear we're showing an increment
a load constant a load from memory and then a store back to memory and we're going to see lots
of these so don't don't slow down and learn this and so up next we're going to learn hexadecimal
because the more data we have the we can't just use base two for everything because it's not a
very dense format